Mabel Vernon Papers
Mabel Vernon Papers
1933-1947
Vernon, Mabel.
54 items (SC).
Papers of the American suffragist, feminist, pacifist (1883-1975). Collection includes incoming correspondence to Mabel Vernon in her capacity as a member of the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom and campaign director of its committee, the People's Mandate to Governments to End War (later re-named the People's Mandate Committee for Inter-American Peace and Cooperation. Notable correspondents include Grace Abbott, Jane Addams, Frank Aydelotte, Irene Bailey, Newton Baker, Pearl S. Buck, Rafael Calderón Guardia, Samuel P. Cadman, Arthur Capper, Carrie Catt, Raymond Clapper, Jacqueline Cochran, Josephus Daniels, Norman H. Davis, Dorothy Canfield Fisher, Abraham Flexner, Zona Gale, Virginia Gildersleeve, Meta Glass, Frank Graham, Inez Irwin, Alfred Landon, Sinclair Lewis, Clare Boothe Luce, Gabriela Mistral, Caroline O'Day, Ruth Owen, Galo Plaza Lasso, Nelson Rockefeller, Leo Rowe, Laurence Steinhardt, Lowell Thomas, M. Carey Thomas, Oswald Villard, Lillian Wald, Wendell Willkie, Mary Woolley, and William Ziff.
149298
Biographical History
Mabel Vernon (1883-1975) was an American Quaker suffragist, feminist, and pacifist. Born in Wilmington, Delaware, she graduated from Friends School in 1901 and from Swarthmore College in 1906. She took a position teaching German and Latin at Radnor High School in Wayne, Pennsylvania, and soon became active in women's rights.
After some time as a member of the American Woman Suffrage Association, Vernon joined with Alice Paul, Lucy Burns, Inez Milholland, Olympia Brown and Crystal Eastman to form the Congressional Union for Women Suffrage (CUWS) in 1913. She was among the more militant suffragists, publicly heckling President Wilson during a speech, organizing huge demonstrations, and coordinating the daily picketing of the White House. After women were granted the vote in 1920, Vernon continued to work for women's causes until the 1930s, when she joined the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom and shifted her focus to peace and disarmament.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Mabel Vernon Papers consists of correspondence and printed material.
Incoming Correspondence is addressed to Mabel Vernon in her capacity as member of the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, and as campaign director of one of its committees, the People's Mandate to Governments to End War. (This was also known as the People's Mandate to End War and the People's Mandate Committee; it was later renamed the People's Mandate Committee for Inter-American Peace and Cooperation.) A few of the items are addressed to the secretaries or other officers of these organizations, including Hannah Clothier Hull, Mary Moss Wellborn, Emma Wold, and Mary E. Woolley.
The correspondence centers around the activities of various pacifist organizations, such as fund-raising, petition signature gathering, and despatching delegations concerned with securing world peace through disarmament. Among those correspondents in support of the Women's International League petition to the President were Dorothy Canfield Fisher, Zona Gale, Inez Haynes Irwin, and Samuel Parkes Cadman. Those who were invited but declined to sign the People's Mandate include Temple Bailey, Ruth Bryan Owen, and Martha Carey Thomas. Correspondents who discuss the work of the People's Mandate Committee include Carrie Chapman Catt, Gabriela Mistral, Galo Plaza Lasso, Nelson Rockefeller, and Leo Rowe.
Some of the correspondents write in general support, not specifying a particular cause or organization. In a letter of May 6, 1937, Clare Boothe Luce writes, "Enclosed is the check. May it, the history of human experience to the contrary, do some good." There are also a few personal letters, including those from Pearl Buck, Arthur Capper, and Lillian Wald.
Printed material includes samples of petitions which were mailed out by the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, which collected names for the People's Mandate Committee. Two returned petitions are from Clarence Darrow and William Allen White. There is also an example of a petition which includes a list of "distinguished persons" who had signed the People's Mandate.
Arrangement of the Collection
Both series are arranged alphabetically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Politics, government and public administration; Activism and social reform; Abbott, Grace, 1878-1939.; Addams, Jane, 1860-1935.; Aydelotte, Frank, 1880-1956.; Bailey, Irene Temple.; Baker, Newton Diehl, 1871-1937.; Buck, Pearl S. (Pearl Sydenstricker), 1892-1973.; Calderón Guardia, Rafael Angel, 1900-1970.; Cadman, Samuel Parkes.; Capper, Arthur, 1865-1951.; Catt, Carrie Chapman, 1859-1947.; Clapper, Raymond, 1892-1944.; Cochran, Jacqueline.; Daniels, Josephus, 1862-1948.; Davis, Norman H.; Fisher, Dorothy Canfield, 1879-1958.; Flexner, Abraham, 1866-1959.; Gale, Zona, 1874-1938.; Gildersleeve, Virginia Crocheron, 1877-; Glass, Meta.; Graham, Frank Porter, 1886-; Irwin, Inez Haynes, 1873-1970.; Landon, Alfred M. (Alfred Mossman), 1887-; Lewis, Sinclair, 1885-1951.; Luce, Clare Boothe, 1903-; Mistral, Gabriela, 1889-1957.; O'Day, Caroline.; Owen, Ruth Bryan.; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979.; Rowe, Leo S.; Steinhardt, Laurence A.; Thomas, Lowell, 1892-1981.; Thomas, M. Carey (Martha Carey), 1857-1935.; Vernon, Mabel.; Villard, Oswald Garrison, 1872-1949.; Wald, Lillian D., 1867-1940.; Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944.; Woolley, Mary Emma.; Ziff, William Bernard.; People's Mandate Committee for Inter-American Peace and Cooperation (U.S.); People's Mandate to Governments to End War.; Plaza Lasso, Galo, 1906-; Women's International League for Peace and Freedom.; Feminists -- United States.; Pacifism.; Pacif ists -- United States.; Pacifists -- Political activity.; Social reformers -- United States.; Correspondence.; Feminists.; Pacifists.; Social reformers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Abbott, Grace, 17 Aug 1937 (Sc 40)
  - Addams, Jane, 10 Dec 1934; 1 letter, 1 signed donation card (Sc 40)
  - Aydelotte, Frank, 11 Mar 1942 (Sc 40)
  - Bailey, (Irene) Temple, 17 Mar 1933 (Sc 40)
  - Baker, Newton Diehl, 9 Mar 1933 (Sc 40)
  - Buck, Pearl S., 11 Jul 1935 (Sc 40)
  - Cadman, Samuel Parkes, 23 May 1936 (Sc 40)
  - Calderón Guardia, Rafael Angel, 31 Mar 1944 (Sc 40)
  - Capper, Arthur, 16 Apr 1937 (Sc 40)
  - Catt, Carrie, 20 Aug 1946 (Sc 40)
  - Clapper, Raymond, 7 Jan 1943 (Sc 40)
  - Cochran, Jacqueline, 24 Oct 1937 (Sc 40)
  - Daniels, Josephus, 10 Jan 1945 (Sc 40)
  - Davis, Norman H., 3 Sep 1941 (Sc 40)
  - Fisher, Dorothy Canfield, 1937; 1943; 2 letters (Sc 40)
  - Flexner, Abraham, 20 Nov 1940 (Sc 40)
  - Gale, Zona, 31 Aug 1935 (Sc 40)
  - Gildersleeve, Virginia Crocheron, 27 Jan 1937 (Sc 40)
  - Glass, Meta, 27 Oct 1937 (Sc 40)
  - Graham, Frank Porter, 30 Jan 1940 (Sc 40)
  - Irwin, Inez Haynes, 18 Jan 1937 (Sc 40)
  - Landon, Alf (Alfred Mossman), 10 Jul 1942 (Sc 40)
  - Lewis, Sinclair, 5 May 1933 (Sc 40)
  - Luce, Clare Boothe, 1937; 1939; 2 letters (Sc 40)
  - Mistral, Gabriela, 1946; 2 letters (Sc 40)
  - O'Day, Caroline, 21 Dec 1934 (Sc 40)
  - Owen, Ruth Bryan, 9 Mar 1933 (Sc 40)
  - Plaza Lasso, Galo, 22 Mar 1946 (Sc 40)
  - Rockefeller, Nelson, 8 Dec 1941 (Sc 40)
  - Rowe, Leo S., 13 Apr 1942 (Sc 40)
  - Steinhardt, Laurence A., 4 Nov 1937 (Sc 40)
  - Thomas, Lowell, 10 Nov 1941 (Sc 40)
  - Thomas, Martha Carey, 3 Mar 1933 (Sc 40)
  - Villard, Oswald Garrison, 4 Jan 1947 (Sc 40)
  - Wald, Lillian D., 13 Jun 1938 (Sc 40)
  - Whitney, Alexander Fell, 25 Jan 1937 (Sc 40)
  - Willkie, Wendell, 10 Feb 1943 (Sc 40)
  - Woolley, Mary Emma, 1936; 1942; 2 letters (Sc 40)
  - Ziff, William Bernard, 29 Sep 1945 (Sc 40)
  - Miscellaneous (Sc 40)
- Printed material
  - Petition: People's Mandate to Governments, 1955 (Sc 40)
    Signers:
    Ballington Booth
    Maud Booth
    Clarence Darrow
    William Allen White